Guide to the Houston Book Clubs research materials, 1993-2007 MS 521
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Houston Book Clubs research materials
1993-2007
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Long, Elizabeth
MS 521
2.75 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The Houston Book Clubs Research Materials consist of material from 1993-2007, including interviews, surveys, emails, reports, essays, lists, and correspondence between Elizabeth Long and members of the literary community. The files were compiled by Elizabeth Long during her study of the role of women's reading groups for her 2003 book "Book Clubs: Women and the Uses of Reading in Everyday Life" (University of Chicago Press).
2.75 linear ft. (6 boxes)
Biographical Sketch
Rice University sociology professor Elizabeth Long's extensive research into the history and growth of reading clubs and their impact on social change is reflected in these papers. Professor Long majored in history at Stanford University and later earned Master's and PhD degrees in sociology at Brandeis University. She joined Rice's Department of Sociology in 1978 after teaching women's studies at Wellesley College and M.I.T. Long has taught a wide variety of courses including the history of sociology, the sociology of gender, feminist social thought, and contemporary sociological theory. In 2003 she was named Texas Professor of the Year by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching and the Council for the Advancement and Support of Education (CASE).
Scope and Contents
The Houston Book Clubs research materials consist of material from 1993-2007, including interviews, surveys, emails, reports, essays, lists, and correspondence between Elizabeth Long and members of the literary community. The files were compiled by Elizabeth Long during her study of the role of women's reading groups for her 2003 book "Book Clubs: Women and the Uses of Reading in Everyday Life" (University of Chicago Press). The surveys and interviews were conducted with Houston area book clubs from 1999-2007 with research focusing on both online book clubs and traditional ones and pertaining to their origins, members, discussions, and processes of book selection. Additionally, the collection contains information from and relating to the 2001 workshop in Cologne, Germany entitled "How literature enters life", sponsored by the International Association for the Empirical Study of Literature and the Media. Research on reading groups is arranged by individual book clubs.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Elizabeth Long, January 2007
Access Restriction
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series I: Research organization and notes
Series II: Book clubs
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Writings / Works
Index Terms
Subjects
Authors; Books and reading -- United States; Literature and society -- United States; Book clubs (Discussion groups); Literature; Women
Document Types
surveys (documents); notes; corrrespondence
- Series I: Research organization and notes, 1999-2000, 71339
  - Organizational Material for Houston Book Club Research, 71354 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Club Master List: Unaffiliated Women, Couples, and unclassified genre, 71353 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book Club Master List: Unaffiliated Men; Unaffiliated: Both, 71352 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book Club Master Lists, 71351 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book Club – Surveys, 71350 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reading Group Survey, 71349 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reading Groups Survey: Elizabeth McBride's Group, 71348 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Networking: Pam Parker, 71347 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of Women's Reading Clubs and Other Clubs in Houston, 1877-1908, 71346 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report of the President of the City Federation of Clubs, May 27, 1903, 71345 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - City Federation of Women's Clubs, 1900 – 1961, 71344 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vintage Reading Group Center: Book Lists, February 22, 2000, 71343 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Houston – Early Efforts to Establish a City Library, 71342 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes, 71341 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 15 Research Notes, 71340 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Book clubs research, 1999-2000, 71298
  - Houston Book Clubs (alphabetical), A's, 71338 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Apostolic Digest, 71337 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Asian Literature: List Serv, 71336 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Axon Club, Houston, Texas. (Organized March 12, 1917), 71335 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baylor Interns' and Residents' Wives Group, 71334 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Book Nook, 71333 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brilliant Books – Surveys, April 2000, 71332 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brilliant Books, List Serv, 71331 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Cadmean Literary Club (Organized 1932), 71330 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Christian Books, 71329 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Christian Books – Surveys, April 2000, 71328 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dark Place Digest, 71327 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dark Place Digest, True Crime Group, 71326 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Horror Book Club, 71325 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Houston Public Library: "Colored Branch", 1907 – 1962, 71324 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rosalie Jordan's Book Group, 71323 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Ladies Reading Club, 71322 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Ladies Reading Club (1901 - 02 Yearbook), 71321 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Medical Biographies Digest. Not Oprah's Book Club, 71320 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Elizabeth Long – Research: On-Line Bookclubs, April 2000, 71319 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Online Book Club Interviews: AFBC and ANFBC, Oct. 1999, 71318 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Online Book Club Interviews: Apostolic, Oct. 1999; Feb. 2000, 71317 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Online Book Club Interviews: Asian Literature, Oct. 1999 - April 2000, 71316 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Online Book Club Interviews: The Book Nook, April 2000, 71315 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Online Moderator Questions and Follow-up, April 2000, 71314 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pagan Literary Guild, 71313 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Surveys: Medical-Biographies; Privacy Issue; Pagan Literary Guild, 71312 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Prizewinning Book Club, 1999-2000, 71311 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Prizewinning Digest #3 - #25 (41), 71310 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Readings and book groups, study clubs, library supporters, 71309 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Reading Loft, 71308 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Reading Loft, April 2000, 71307 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Marsha Recknagel's Group, 71306 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Romance Readers Club, 1999-2000, 71305 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Romance Readers Club-Digest #28, 71304 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Salsa Book Group, 71303 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - TALAR-LITFORUM List; True Crime Group, 71302 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - TALAR-LITFORUM #71-85 (90), 71301 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Vampire Book Club, 71300 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Vampire Book Club, 71299 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1993-2000, 71290
  - AFBC e-mails, 71296 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - ANFBC e-mails, 71295 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1993-1999, 71294 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1994-96, 71293 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1993-1997, 71292 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Research Correspondence, April 2000, 71291 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Writings / Works, 1994-2001, 71275
  - "History of the Book", 71289 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - "History of the Book" – Draft of essay: "Middle-Class African-American Women's Literary Practices at the Turn of the Century", 71288 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Blackwell Contract and Correspondence with Elizabeth Long, 1994-97, 71287 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Schools and the Reading Textbook" (Draft), 71286 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Draft of Chapter for volume IV (unidentified book) (1998), 71285 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Essay regarding goals of Cultural Studies, 1994, 71284 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Lyceum to Library: A Chapter in the Cultural History of Houston", 71283 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - IGEZ Workshop (Cologne, Germany) 2001, 71282 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Workshop: "How Literature Enters Life" (2001) – Program and Participants, 71281 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Workshop: "How Literature Enters Life" – Abstracts, 71280 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Papers submitted for Workshop: "How Literature Enters Life", 71279 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Workshop: "How Literature Enters Life", 71278 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Handbuch Lesen, 1999, 71277 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Copies of hand-written extracts (or reviews) of books and literary materials, 71276 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series V: Oral History interviews
  - Oral history interview DVDs (16), 2007 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    This file includes 16 DVDs of oral history interviews: Beverly Aderholf, Shirley Boyd, Frances Callendar, Penny Cerling, Delia Cowles, M.J. Figard, Lois Guerning, Peggy Hester, Margaret Kaye, Gayle McMurrow, Kay McStay, Barbara Nelson, Diane Roberts, Sandra Walsh, Linda Yarger, Pam Young
  - Oral history interviews Release Forms, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Printed transcript: Conversations with Women who Read, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 3)